There are 12 of them.
12 stadiums built across Europe,
imagined by the most daring architects and built by thousands of workers and engineers.
12 gigantic arenas selected to host matches for a global event,
the 2020 European Football Championship.
Embark on a unique tour of Europe to discover the most beautiful stadiums on the continent.
In this episode,
The match will pit the National Arena of Bucharest in Romania against the Pouchkas Arena of Budapest in Hungary.
On one hand,
an arena resembling an amphitheater,
equipped with a retractable roof,
is designed to withstand the most powerful earthquakes.
It's magnificent.
From the outside,
It looks like the Colosseum in Rome.
And inside,
We are safe from earthquakes.
On the other hand,
a newly constructed enclosure
ready to become the new emblem of Hungarian sport,
preserving the legendary symbols of a stadium that no longer exists.
The Hungarian people loved the old stadium very much,
We were all very attached to it.
The biggest challenge,
It was about figuring out how to make people love the new stadium.
How could he possibly take the very special place that the old one held?
Bucharest and Budapest,
two stadiums located in Eastern Europe,
links between the past and the future.
Let's begin our journey in Romania and its capital,
the largest city in the country,
with its 2 million inhabitants.
This unique city is a bridge between East and West.
These wide avenues,
legacy of the communist era,
are dotted with gardens and magnificent parks,
like Liamanoliu Park,
located east of the capital,
the city's green lung.
This is it.
in 1953,
that the first national stadium was built.
He played a decisive role in the development of the territory.
A park and sports facilities have been built all around the stadium.
Today,
This is Liamanoliu Park.
The installation of these infrastructures,
very close to the city centre,
has generated a new dynamic for this area.
All the surrounding neighborhoods,
like Pantelimon or Titan,
developed at that time.
It was truly a trigger for urban growth.
The historic stadium in Bucharest has hosted major sporting competitions.
And over the years it has become a national institution.
The old stadium from the 1950s was a flat stadium.
It was very large and could accommodate well over 60,000 spectators.
It also served as a performance venue.
for people like Ceausescu,
to convey political messages.
The stadium is not only located in the heart of the city of Bucharest,
but also in the hearts of Romanians.
In 1953,
The stadium is built inside a kind of crater surrounded by embankments.
In the 2000s,
The stadium is old and worn.
The authorities then decided to completely demolish the structure in order to rebuild a new enclosure on the same site.
Removing these 125,000 m3 of earth would have had a significant cost and lengthened the construction time.
if it had been superior.
The engineers decided to reuse the fill and integrate it into the new enclosure.
They move the earth and form a 6-meter-high embankment along three-quarters of the perimeter.
The three stands rest upon them,
north,
east and south,
of the new stadium.
The main stand,
As for her,
then lands lower down,
at the level of the arrival of the spectators.
This solution prevented wasting land and also improved the spectator experience.
When we arrive at the stadium,
We are at ground level.
To enter,
We have to climb the stairs to reach the embankment.
And then,
We have a magnificent view.
You can stroll around the stadium overlooking the park,
6 meters above.
And to enjoy what surrounds us.
Upon entering the enclosure,
The 63,000 spectators arrive halfway up the stands.
From there,
The two levels of bleachers stand out very distinctly and you can walk all around them with an unobstructed view of the entire field.
But the architects and engineers didn't just work on the interior aesthetics of the stadium.
With its shape and repetitions,
The design of the national arena is reminiscent in many ways of a masterpiece of ancient architecture.
the Colosseum.
The Bucharest arena bears obvious similarities to Roman arenas.
For example,
all the pillars,
the vertical columns that support the arena,
remind us of the different levels of the test.
the Roman era.
Other elements of the perimeter,
The Bucharest arena has an oval facade.
The other point of similarity is the point of similarity of the Bucharest arena.
One of the biggest filling problems with the Colosseum,
That's the roof.
The architects installed what is called a velarium,
exactly like in Roman amphitheaters.
A movable sail that can be opened and closed as needed.
The layout of the stands in the national arena echoes the slightly inclined seating of the Colosseum.
But the national arena is also a contemporary stadium,
as shown by the colors of its seats,
which contrast sharply with the building's antique aesthetic.
These colors represent the Romanian national flag.
red,
yellow and blue.
It's a stadium built by Romanians.
for Romanians,
Therefore, the national flag had to be present.
Even when there are no spectators,
The stadium seems alive.
We look around and we get the impression that there are people.
This is one of the main reasons why the seats were colored this way.
to make the stadium come alive,
so that it looks inhabited.
By combining tradition and modernity,
The designers have succeeded in making this new building a landmark for the entire country.
In the capital of Hungary,
in Budapest,
Another national stadium was also demolished to make way for a new one.
the Puskás Arena.
This city has had a tumultuous history.
Budapest has a new face today.
Many buildings are being restored and,
like its stadium,
new architectural pieces stand out.
This new arena with a capacity of nearly 70,000 seats has just been completed.
An extraordinary construction project.
since it is the largest public building in Hungary and, above all,
a symbol for all the Hungarian people.
The stadium is built on the same site as the legendary old stadium.
Nepstadion,
the people's stadium
which therefore had to be destroyed.
This 100,000-seat structure was inaugurated in 1953.
It has been the site of the national team's greatest achievements.
A legend in the history of sport,
nicknamed the Golden 11,
led by its star striker,
Ferenc Puskas,
the idol of the entire country.
In Taldunay,
32 caps for the Hungarian national team,
remembers that time.
Those were great matches.
The stadium was always full.
And at the time,
Football was a celebration for everyone.
There were some very great footballers,
like those who were part of the golden eleven.
The Hungarian team won almost all of its matches.
They were truly the best team in the world.
The atmosphere in the stadium was truly fantastic.
1954.
One particularly memorable match left a lasting impression.
A friendly match between Hungary and England,
which ended in a 7-1 victory for the Hungarians.
The stadium also hosted,
repeatedly,
the European Athletics Championships.
Through these various sporting events,
The people's stadium has become a symbol for the entire country.
Over time,
The structure had completely deteriorated and demolition was inevitable.
The Hungarian authorities have therefore decided to rebuild on the same site a
ultra-modern stadium.
But they gave the designer a specific mission.
To preserve the soul of the old one within this new enclosure.
This is Giorgis Kardély,
renowned Hungarian architect,
who was chosen to take on the challenge.
Football fan,
Giorgi often came to watch matches in the old stadium when he was a child.
How can you transmit the spirit and soul of a stadium if you have to destroy it completely?
To begin with,
The most important thing was to preserve the location and position of the stadium.
So the new stadium is positioned in exactly the same place as the old one.
Why is this so important?
Because people have become accustomed to the image of this building in the city.
And above all,
They've adopted everyone's habits.
always take the same route to get to the stadium.
And that,
It was very important to keep it too.
In addition,
The stadium is one of the three elements that create unity in the structure of the city.
We leave from the Budapest Arena,
then the garden of statues,
the dromos,
as it's called here,
And we finally arrive at the Pushkas stadium.
The perfect alignment of the enclosure with the statue garden and the Budapest arena was an essential prerequisite for the builders.
The architect then had to imagine what this new stadium should look like so that the Hungarian people could identify with it.
We needed to find characteristic elements of the stadium that could be saved from the old one.
Our goal was to incorporate them into the new one,
so that they integrate perfectly in an ordinary way.
organic to our new enclosure.
During the demolition of the old stadium,
It was therefore decided to keep only one original element.
The brick building that formerly housed the press center and which can be recognized in many archive photos.
This building remains as the sole vestige of the past.
in the middle of the construction site of a new, ultra-modern stadium.
In the old stadium,
the tower served as a press center.
And in the next stadium,
We're going to give it a new function.
The museum will be housed in this tower.
We want to keep this building in its original form.
both outdoors and indoors.
Actually,
We wanted to keep it because it gives an excellent image of 1950s architecture.
This perfectly illustrates the political climate of the time when plans for such a building were drawn up.
This is what is called the socialist-realist style.
And that fits well with the function of the museum we envisioned.
The Hungarian architect also wanted to draw inspiration from the old stadium when designing the exterior of the new venue.
The old stadium had a very striking feature,
the pillars of the staircases that provided access to all levels of the stands.
In each photo taken of the stadium,
You can clearly see these pillars and especially the patterns that...
which allowed one to see outside towards the city.
It was a kind of very fine mesh,
Made of concrete.
The façade of the new stadium is therefore composed of 36 stairwells,
distributed evenly around the stadium.
All are covered with a concrete wall open to the outside and designed according to the same patterns as those of the old stadium.
But even if the result appears identical,
The structure is actually completely different.
At the time,
Specialized workers had built and assembled hundreds of small components on site with impressive precision.
For the new Pushkas Arena,
The designers found a much more ingenious and easier-to-implement solution.
Each pillar is actually made up of about ten prefabricated panels.
hoisted using a crane and slid directly into a steel rail.
By preserving these motifs from the past,
The Pouchkas Arena perpetuates the history of the people's stadium and can make all Hungarians proud.
The Hungarian people loved the old stadium very much.
We were all very attached to it.
The biggest challenge,
It was about figuring out how to make people love the new stadium.
How could he possibly take the very special place that the old one held?
After 4 years of work,
The stadium is finally finished.
The spectators immediately embraced their new cathedral.
Thanks to its architectural features,
It reminds them of the old enclosure.
At only 9 years old,
900 kilometers,
The Bucharest National Arena is located in an extremely monitored seismic zone.
Romania is the European Union country most vulnerable to earthquakes.
In 1977,
An unprecedented catastrophe has left its mark on people's minds.
The Vrancea earthquake,
with a magnitude of 7.2 on the Richter scale,
struck Romania
Moldova and Bulgaria,
causing more than 1,500 deaths and 11,000 injuries.
To prevent a similar tragedy from happening again,
The builders had to construct a framework capable of withstanding the most powerful earthquakes.
The understanding between architects and engineers was fundamental to meeting this challenge.
In my opinion,
It was really important to talk about earthquake risks from the very beginning with the architects.
I wanted to make sure that we would develop an optimal design from an architectural point of view.
both architectural and structural.
Good design is possible when the architect works with a structural engineer from the start of the project.
Since the architect is responsible for both aesthetics and functionality,
He has the last word.
But when he listens to the structural engineer,
He can adapt some of his ideas by taking his recommendations into account.
Earthquake-resistant construction involves analyzing the interaction between the building and the ground and predicting the potential consequences of an earthquake.
It then makes it possible to create a building that can withstand it.
Seismic forces are inertial forces.
This means that the forces arrive at every point of the structure.
They need to be directed towards the walls to accumulate and then sent back to the ground.
To ensure the stability of the structure,
The engineers developed four specific anti-seismic features.
Usually,
A structure of this size is supported by 40 pillars.
Here,
The engineers added 80 additional pillars.
6 seismic joints,
distributed all around the perimeter,
have been added.
The 6 sub-parts can then move independently of each other.
without damaging the entire structure.
The engineers also built reinforcing walls perpendicular to the stands,
distributed all around the stadium along the axis of each of the 120 pillars.
To complete the system,
a wall parallel to the stands goes around the perimeter of the enclosure.
Finally,
below the upper tiers,
Support walls have been put in place to reinforce the structure.
Using conventional construction methods,
The upper row of the stands is shaped like a step.
Here,
when viewed from the ground,
the top row is flat.
This is a unique characteristic.
I find it very aesthetically pleasing that it's straight.
As an architect,
I think it's really beautiful.
But it didn't come from a designer's idea.
This was necessary to ensure it was as rigid as possible and could withstand the threat of earthquakes.
Architects and engineers therefore designed and integrated as many solutions as possible to strengthen the structure and make it less vulnerable to earthquakes.
Extraordinary equipment for an extraordinary site.
In Budapest,
The manufacturers had to face another challenge.
Find a formwork system to build the enclosure columns in record time and in complete safety.
To support the steel roof structure,
36 pillars with variable geometry are installed.
structures 45 meters high must be built.
But above all,
These pillars must be completed simultaneously.
because the arrival of an exceptional crane from Belgium to lift the roof elements is scheduled.
For the engineers and workers, a race against time then begins.
They will use a specific formwork that allows these gigantic columns to be built simultaneously and at the same pace.
The principle is to advance the construction of the pillar.
step by step,
from bottom to top.
To achieve this,
They chose to use a three-level formwork system.
The first two floors of the pillar must first be built using a classic formwork technique.
From there,
We can then install a system perfectly adapted to the height and shape of the pillar.
Three platforms are used by the workers to carry out the work.
The lower platform is used for finishing and cleaning work.
The middle platform is where the formwork elements are located to build the upper level.
The last platform allows workers to pour concrete into the formwork.
Once the level is completed,
The entire system is raised to the next level.
Thanks to the adaptable formwork,
which can be retracted up to 75 cm,
the wall takes on the desired thickness or shape.
The levels can be linked together in this way,
while respecting the shape of the pillars envisioned by the architects.
In total,
There are 10 levels per pillar.
To meet the deadlines and erect the 36 pillars before the crane arrives,
250 formworks of this type were required.
And to make matters more complicated,
in this country where the temperature range is significant,
The concrete pouring always had to take place at the same time of day.
It was necessary to ensure that the surface of each pillar was a uniform grey colour.
For that,
The concrete formwork had to be put in place at roughly the same time of day.
Otherwise,
because evaporation mechanisms differ depending on the time of day,
The color of the concrete could have been different from one level to another.
The use of this exceptional construction device offers several advantages.
The main advantage of these two systems is that when you are on fairly high floors,
in the fourth,
fifth or sixth,
We don't need to separate them at each stage.
They can be hoisted together,
all at once.
thanks to the crane.
Another important advantage,
It's a safe system that allows workers to work in a secure environment.
protected by a fence at a very high altitude.
And finally,
The crane's usage time is short.
It's quite quick to simply upgrade the system from one level to the next.
The pillars are therefore not built one after the other,
but all at the same time.
This system allows progress on the different pillars simultaneously.
While waiting for the concrete to dry on one level,
The process is then carried out at the next level on a neighboring pillar.
So,
The 36 pillars were completed in just one year.
just in time for the crane to hoist the imposing steel roof.
At an exceptional stage,
exceptional project.
And what if at the Pouchkas Arena,
36 pillars were built directly on site,
at the National Arena,
The teams had to erect 120 of them.
They poured the concrete into formwork on site.
But for the...
40 columns that will support the roof,
They were built more than 1500 km from Bucharest.
in Neumark, Germany,
then transported by heavy goods vehicle.
But building all the parts in Germany was too complex and expensive.
So, the German architects,
in collaboration with Romanian architects,
had another idea.
Imagine that we have built a huge rigid tent like a circus tent.
It's a practical solution.
A large tent, 50 meters long and 50 meters wide.
In this tent,
The parts were prefabricated.
which were then stored for a certain period of time.
When they were ready,
They were brought to the construction site and stored until they were installed.
The stands,
the stairs,
the ramps,
The small posts and even the transverse wall were built directly on the construction site.
Yet,
The constraints imposed by seismic risks complicate the task of the teams.
Because in order to withstand earthquakes,
The prefabricated parts need to be larger.
therefore heavier.
With small prefabricated elements,
Cranes can be used.
These are the same cranes that are used for other tasks on the construction site.
For large elements or roof elements,
We use specific cranes,
which have greater load capacities.
When building with prefabricated materials,
The equipment used to transport and install the components plays a fundamental role.
because the loads are very heavy.
The design of the prefabricated parts must be final.
because it is impossible to modify an element once it has been installed.
This requires extremely rigorous planning and meticulous organization.
but it has many advantages.
Construction time is much faster.
The quality is perfect.
No further treatment is needed.
cleaning or smoothing with plastic.
We don't need to wait for the concrete to harden before moving on to the next step.
We can continue to build the different parts as we go along.
It's really satisfying to see how quickly these Lego pieces were assembled and clicked together properly.
Everything worked perfectly.
Once all the prefabricated elements are installed,
The structure needs to be fitted with a roof.
To avoid weakening the structure in the face of an earthquake,
The engineers opted for an extremely lightweight cover.
The lighter your roof,
The more it will withstand earthquakes.
And that's also how a lightweight structure is stronger than any beam system.
megabeams or other structures
used in a stadium.
And to ensure the roof is as strong as possible,
The engineers installed a reinforcement system.
steel cables.
The roof rests partly on the bleachers and is connected to them by 8 pairs of cables in a cross shape.
Since there are several of them,
if one pair is missing,
There's always enough.
But the key is to minimize dead weight,
the weight of the roof,
so that the acceleration is not destructive.
As in many stadiums across the globe,
Architects and engineers were also involved in the creation of these structures.
opted for a bicycle wheel roof system.
The trick is to find a system that prevents the forces acting on lightweight structures from simply being transferred into the ground.
but to be counterbalanced.
Systems called bicycle wheel systems are now very commonly used.
That's what we did for the roof structure of the Bucharest stadium.
It's the same principle, but more complex.
And that's what we decided to use.
To be able to have both a fixed and a retractable part,
The roof of the national arena is very elaborate.
Here,
Two bicycle wheel systems were combined,
one for the fixed part and one for the retractable part.
For the fixed part of the roof,
The 40 columns connected by 18-meter-long beams form the rim of the first wheel.
This is called a compression ring.
A system of taut cables connected to the center of the roof structure represents the spokes.
They will be attached to the rim of the second wheel.
Again,
Cables are stretched to the center of the second bicycle wheel.
The hub of the second wheel is the central point of the entire system.
It's a large 40-ton steel piece that houses the retractable roof.
To ensure the entire roof is balanced,
Vertical tubes were installed in the center of the two wheels.
Cables from the central piece pass over the steel tubes and attach to the beams of the compression ring.
So,
Two wheels with very distinct functions are suspended thanks to this wiring system.
But the most striking feature of the national arena's roof,
It's the fully automated removable system of its retractable roof.
This technological marvel,
which spans 9,000 square meters and weighs over 25,000 tons,
It installs in just 8 minutes.
The roof covering is stored in a large box,
which is called the video cube,
located at a height of 42 meters.
It is equipped with 4 giant screens and several speakers for sound.
The box can be lowered to the ground for maintenance.
Dan Radou takes us inside this extraordinary structure.
So here we are in the video cube.
It's a giant box,
It's gigantic.
Here we have the four electric motors that allow the video cube to move up and down.
All these cables are electrical.
Electrical cables provide power for all the installations found there.
The surface area of ​​these video walls is 36 square meters.
And the power of the sound broadcast throughout the stadium can reach 70,000 watts.
At the controls of this ultra-sophisticated, state-of-the-art system,
Katalin Soare,
Director of Operations.
Here,
We are in the control room.
And we find ourselves facing the two control panels.
One for the roof and one for the video cube.
The two screens are linked.
On this one,
We receive the data transmitted by the weather station on the retractable roof.
You can see the speed in kilometers per hour.
the temperature.
Depending on the wind speed,
The system goes into safe mode.
If the wind exceeds 20 km/h, for example,
The station is blocking the roof mechanism.
which can no longer be activated.
The blockage lasts 60 minutes.
At that moment,
if the wind has calmed down,
The mechanism is unlocked.
To proceed with the opening,
The video cube needs to be lowered by 8 meters.
Then,
Carts transport and unfold the membrane onto steel cables which,
in addition to supporting the weight of the structure,
act as a rail.
This system is fully automated and secure.
When you proceed with opening...
You can see the pressure level and real-time position of each engine,
whether they are late or not.
Each motor is independent and their position is shown as a percentage of distance traveled.
Once in place,
A system of hydraulic jacks attaches the membrane and puts the cables under tension.
The roof is then perfectly rigid.
At the end,
The system automatically stops the carriages of the 32 motors to secure the entire mechanism.
And we,
from our control room,
We can verify that each engine is properly stopped on our monitors.
Although extremely complex,
This system appears incredibly simple when you watch it unfold.
The roof resembles a kind of giant umbrella,
very light,
which covers the enclosure and protects the spectators,
but without giving them the impression of being locked up.
In Budapest,
The Puskas Arena is also equipped with a roof,
built using state-of-the-art techniques.
Unlike the old stadium, which was completely open,
The stands today are completely covered.
One of the biggest challenges for the engineers was to manufacture the immense roof that covers the entirety of the stadium's stands.
A 10,000-tonne metal structure resting atop the stadium's 36 stairwells,
creating a gigantic cantilever 90 meters long.
The elements that make up the roof are first manufactured on the ground.
Around the stadium,
It's a veritable giant Meccano set that has been organized.
composed of hundreds of metal tubes that workers must assemble.
The roof is divided into 36 identical segments.
Each segment consists of three distinct elements which are first assembled separately.
They are then hoisted one by one to the top of the stairwell and fixed to each other to obtain the total length of the cantilever.
From the moment the first beam is installed,
This high-risk operation required the use of exceptional resources.
This structure, composed of three metal elements, reaches 80 to 90 meters in length and weighs more than 250 tons.
To lift such a structure,
It was necessary to bring in a crane of which there are only 8 examples in Europe.
capable of lifting 1000 tonnes and the load curve is 130 metres.
The crane will therefore lift the three elements that make up each segment of the framework and allow them to be fixed to each other at the top.
This operation will have to be repeated on all 36 stairwells of the stadium.
In total,
That makes 36 times three elements to hoist up there.
Barnabas Sighetti leads us to the top of the stadium.
stadium,
at the point where the metal framework and the concrete meet.
The biggest technical challenge of the project,
It's this roof structure.
The length of the roof varies between 80 and 90 meters depending on its position.
It's very, very long.
This corresponds to the size of a football pitch and the points of support on which...
The structural elements rest relatively close to each other, and therefore the forces they must withstand are truly enormous. In the first phase of design, the engineers considered using traditional solutions to secure the stadium roof.
stadium with classic steel components.
But they found that with this type of system,
the strength of the framework was not guaranteed and cracks could appear in the areas subjected to the greatest stresses.
To support the 10,000 tonnes of the roof,
The engineers resorted to a novel solution.
Each of the 36 segments that make up the framework rests on 4 supports placed at the top of each stairwell.
It is at the level of these four steel pieces that all the stresses due to the weight of the framework are distributed.
At this location,
conventional fixings would likely fail with such a long overhang.
The designers therefore invented a system of invisible cables.
Eight groups of metal cables are attached to each plate and are then pulled downwards under tension.
They thus recover the stresses of the framework,
then they are fixed to the inside of the stairwell walls.
In total,
to support the enormous weight of the roof,
There are nearly 11,000 cables that attach to supports placed at the top of the stairwells and pass through the concrete walls of the Pouchkas Arena.
On the construction site,
The workers are stretching the long cables that can be seen in some places of the stadium already embedded in the concrete of the facade.
This project is a major challenge for us.
A public building of this size had never been built in Hungary before.
We're talking about an enormous size.
Can you imagine?
The amount of cable incorporated into the stadium would allow Budapest to be connected to Barcelona or London.
In total,
The stadium was built in 32 months.
And the schedule was scrupulously followed.
We inaugurated the stadium ten days ahead of schedule.
We wanted to do it on November 25th.
November 25th is the anniversary of Hungary's most important match.
In 1953,
The Hungarian team has beaten the English team six times at Wembley.
It was a historic victory and our team was led by Puskas.
We would have liked to inaugurate the stadium on the anniversary of this event.
but the UEFA competition calendar did not allow it.
We were in the qualifying period for...
of the European Championship and we had to adapt to the international competition calendar.
November 15th was the only available day and we had to accelerate our schedule and finish the work 10 days ahead of the planned deadline.
For these men who participated in the construction of this temple of football,
The completion of this major project is generating a lot of emotion.
We are very happy.
It was a pleasure to work on this.
It wasn't even really a job,
but something that was important to us.
Everyone who participated in it considers it one of the most important projects of their life.
And for the spectators,
The new Puskas Arena is a real success.
The traffic routes are open to the outside and connect the stadium to the city.
Many facilities have been improved to welcome visitors and offer them a unique experience.
On match nights,
The stadium can light up in different colors.
When Hungary plays,
It is the national flag that colors the facade.
and strengthens the fervor of the supporters.
The National Arena in Bucharest and the Pouchkas Arena in Budapest have managed to reinvent themselves,
while respecting the legendary characteristics of the old enclosures that have now been destroyed.
It is a very important place for the inhabitants of Bucharest.
Not only is it the largest stadium in Romania,
But above all, it's the most beautiful stadium in the country.
And I am very proud to have this opportunity to be here and to work here.
We are pleased to have built a new stadium that truly resembles the previous one.
the people's stadium.
By looking at and comparing the two stages,
The resemblance is striking.
We are really pleased that people like it and that this performance is
100% Hungarian.
It's good that we stayed within our budget and deadlines.
These two 21st-century arenas can now write a new chapter in their country's history.